foreign
[Music]
and as always we have a whole lot of
questions that we're going to discuss uh
questions that you all have asked in the
comments and elsewhere but as always
before that let me greet you all and see
who all is there with us on the live
chat I can see
auspicious doomsday tatagat Kushi Rani
Deepak divyanshu nikhil The Landmark
venkat ready R2 futu manohar daddy Zhong
Tejas pranav Max Renzo yuvraj Aditya
Roshan siddhant Mazar fatty just ate IPS
.
Durga Harvey on Wheels Kesh of xkgb
agent Shaheen pankaj Kumar tyagi Kishore
C4 D2 Suman harsh very yo yo go go
Satish siddhant Never Satisfied Akshay
Nandan Ashwin Shivan Shri mango Hindu
Sher Putin chiching Vladimir Harvey
ropes Aditi Stone 420 Jay Rana the
private mover abhinav santanu Mr
child of India
the bhagat
Varun
and lots of other people good evening
good day all of you and thank you so
much for being on the show with uh with
me tonight this wonderful fine evening
over here
so with that done
uh let us get into the questions shall
we let's get right into the questions as
always
um
okay what's the first question here's
the first question it's by a number of
people
and Shaheen how will the U.S midterm
results affect India and the rest of the
world the U.S midterms is right around
the corner if the Republicans win the
midterms now how will it affect Ukraine
and what will the foreign policy be like
towards India will it be a little bit
better and shine says what are your
thoughts on the U.S midterm elections in
2022 how will the results impact India
and the rest of the world's geopolitical
uh landscape yeah good question so let's
see what the results are like I mean I
discussed this yesterday on the uh on
the Indian interest podcast and let's
see what the results are like I mean it
was still not clear who's winning now it
looks like the Democrat the Democrats
may be winning the the U.S Senate
uh so let's see what the results are
like right now
uh yes here we are this is the current
scenario the Senate results officially
it's 48 48 Democrats 48 Democrats are in
blue and the Republicans are in red you
need 51 for a majority
so it looks I mean in some places I'm
hearing that the Democrats are winning
but over here it looks like it's still
uh not yet decided so
this is the situation in the U.S Senate
which is a higher uh the Upper House
and the lower house is the U.S House of
Representatives it's 211 for the
Republicans 203 for the Democrats
so yeah it's still not quite clear who's
going to win the elections who's go and
which way it's going to go it could be
that the Republicans could have a thin
very thin majority in the house and in
the Senate it could be either way I'm
sorry in the house it could be the
Democrats who may
the Republicans the reds are the
Republicans in the House of
Representatives it could be the
Republicans who would get most likely
possibly from what it looks like over
here a thin majority perhaps and in the
Senate it could be the Democrats or the
Republicans we're not quite sure so
that's uh the situation right now so the
question is obviously very good or
uh the question is
one second let me yeah here we are so
how will this results affect India and
the rest of the world will it change the
the U.S policy towards Ukraine to change
the foreign policy towards India how
will this all impact the rest of the
world and on the geopolitical landscape
so
from the geopolitics perspective when we
talk about the U.S foreign policy the US
is the most powerful nation in the world
it's the sole superpower and that's why
anything that happens in the US is going
to affect the world it's and and the U.S
foreign policy is something that every
nation in the world needs to keep a very
close uh watch on yes so um
there are three scenarios one scenario
is that the Republicans win the Upper
House the senate in the lower house
which is uh the House of Representatives
that seems unlikely but if that happens
then there will be no impediment or
obstacle towards the Republican Party
form of framing any kind of legislation
it wants and governing the country as
they want yeah so that is the optimum uh
result for the Democrats for the ruling
party the ruling party is the other
Democrats so if they win the upper house
which is the Senate and the lower house
which is the uh House of Representatives
then the Democrats will have absolutely
no impediment in ruling the country for
the next two years anyway they want and
for framing any kind of legislation that
they want the other scenario is that uh
the Democrats win the Upper House the
Senate and the Republicans win the lower
house which is the uh House of
Representatives which could make things
very problematic for the Democrats who
are currently the Joe Biden is a
Democrat yeah so so it could make things
difficult for them they will not be able
to pass any kind of legislation they
want and it could essentially make Joe
Biden a lame duck president who is
ruling only a name but he cannot um
cannot get any legislation or any any
policies passed yes because if the lower
house is controlled by the Republicans
then they will not allow that to happen
and if the Republicans uh win the lower
house as seems kind of likely right now
then they could launch all kinds of
Investigations on the Democrats
especially about the U.S withdrawal from
Afghanistan which is a which is an
interesting example it was a chaotic
disastrous withdrawal from Afghanistan
yes and uh they could also launch
investigations into the conduct of Joe
Biden himself and his son Hunter Biden
so it could be very um it could not be
very nice it could be yeah that's a
uncomfortable situation for the ruling
party the Democratic party so that's
what happens if the Democrats won win
the Senate and the Republicans win the
house the third scenario is that the
Republicans win the Senate and the house
that's also a possibility uh so if that
happens that's gonna be even worse for
uh Joe Biden and his Democratic party
yes because in that case there will be
all kinds of problems cropping up for
them and they will essentially Joe
Budden eventually be a completely
totally ineffective and lame duck
president
so uh now what does this mean for the
world
uh when it comes to U.S foreign policy
it's typically the same more or less the
same whether it's the Republicans who
are in power or the Democrats more or
less the same because much of the
foreign policies the bulk of the foreign
policy see the see the the core of the
foreign policy is dictated from the
Pentagon not from the White House the
White House will do certain things for
instance when Trump was President he
launched this trade war against China
and uh
so you will have some some effect from
the White House but overall the the
policy is run by the bureaucracy the
foreign policy is done by the
bureaucracy which resides in the
Pentagon uh some people would call it
the Deep state or whatever they want to
call it yeah so uh typically whether the
Republican Republicans are in power or
the Democrats the foreign policy remains
moral at the same it's an imperialistic
foreign policy it's a hegemonic foreign
policy it's it's its objective is to
sustain and preserve and and perpetuate
the U.S Supremacy and hegemony over the
world yes protect the supply chains
protect the infrastructure protect the
uh dollar as the reserve currency and
the wage Wars wherever required in order
to feed the military industrial complex
all of that and no president would dare
to go against that yes uh so overall I
think that it will not change even if
let's say the the Republicans are able
to win the lower house and maybe even
the upper house it will not really
change the foreign policy too much the
U.N U.S foreign foreign policy too much
of course when it comes to uh the
presidency itself well
historically in recent times like the
past two three decades the Republicans
have typically had a better approach
towards India than the Democrats so when
we talk about Republicans we're talking
about people like Donald Trump like
George W bush uh that's the two that
come to mind yeah and when we talk about
democratic presidents we're talking
about people like uh Barack Obama and
right now we have Joe Biden so right now
Joe Biden is the president and the
Americans have not appointed a governor
I'm sorry an ambassador to India for
nearly two years that position is lying
vacant which is extremely strange
because India is one of the major
nations in the world yeah I mean nobody
can deny that and it's an emerging power
it's in emerging great power it's a
significant Nation now of India in in
global geopolitics in economics and all
that and yet the Americans are are not
willing to appoint an ambassador to such
an important nation that that kind of
shows it's it's
designed to convey certain signals and
messages to India yeah and to the world
as well that they are not pleased with
the way India is is conducting its
business and the the way India I mean
whatever policies uh domestic policies
foreign policy economic policies Etc
India is pursuing the Democrats are not
happy with it and the U.S
uh
foreign policy State Department is not
happy with what's going on and and
typically when you have a Democratic
president the the uh approach towards
India is a little bit harsher and it's a
little bit less friendly it's a little
bit colder it's a little bit more
antagonistic and adversarial as opposed
to when a Republican president is in in
the White House typically it's it's like
a change of maybe five to ten percent
overall the foreign policy is more or
less the same I mean when when Mr Modi
was became prime minister in 2014 Mr
Obama was the president of the U.S and
Mr Modi was able to establish a very
good relationship with Obama yeah and
things were going well and then when
Trump came to power Mr Modi was able to
establish an even better relationship
with Mr Trump right now I don't know
what sort of relationship is there with
Mr Biden it's very hard to tell what
happens with Mr Biden but yeah that's
how it is so
and what about Ukraine
well I think even if the Democrats lose
the house or even the Congress I don't
think the foreign policy towards Ukraine
and Russia will change much yeah so
um so I don't think it's going to change
much because like I said overall the
foreign policy is dictated from the
Pentagon from the from the uh unelected
bureaucracy that that runs the foreign
policy the state department these people
are essentially there for Life once they
once they get in
and uh
and that's how it is yeah so I don't
think it's going to have much of a
change much of uh the foreign policy is
going to change much it is still going
to stay more or less the same there is a
significant amount of bipartisanship
when it comes to the foreign policy the
the two parties the Democrats and
Republicans they differ a lot and they
are they disagree a lot when it comes to
domestic affairs when it comes to
domestic policy gun control abortion
women's rights and and what not right
all those things these are big issues
when it comes to domestic policies and
domestic politics domestic issues but
when it comes to foreign policy they are
a very more or less very much aligned
bipartisan uh alignment alignment when
it comes to foreign policy so I don't
think it's going to affect India too
much or the rest of the world too much
no matter what happens but of course if
the Republicans are able to take over
the lower house let's say
then they could create a lot of trouble
for Joe Biden and for the Democratic
party and the government there could be
government shutdowns like we saw in the
past in the U.S there could be
investigations launched like I said
which could be embarrassing or even
damaging to the president and his family
and to the Democratic party and a whole
lot is going on uh so even now we're not
entirely sure as to what direction this
is going to take will the Democrats be
able to win the Senate the Upper House
in some places I hear that they've
already won the upper house but when you
look at the Google latest scorecard or
whatever you want to call it uh it still
says 48.48.
or when it comes to the Senate and the
upper house is uh we have a republican
lead there gop211 is opposed to
Democrats 203. so it's still uh I would
say a little early to call maybe in a
few days we will have a better idea of
what's Happening until then we will wait
and watch and I will certainly revisit
this issue and and look at it with fresh
eyes Maybe by by next weekend when we
have the next set of live streams
so overall I don't think no matter what
happened I think that no matter what
happens it will not change U.S foreign
policy much because the president is
still a Democrat and the the
the the um Pentagon still has its own
views which don't change and overall
there is bipartisan agreement when it
comes to foreign policy so it's not
going to change things too much
okay himanshu says since you've spoken
in your episode with ranveer that Donald
Trump's contribution to the US has been
lowest when compared to his predecessors
predecessors do you think he can still
return to attain the top post once again
after the Biden presidency term gets
over nimit says what are your views on
the U.S midterm elections do you think
this type of Red Wave can be seen in
2024 presidential election will Donald
Trump do a comeback
so essentially these two questions are
about the future the political future of
Donald Trump will Donald Trump be able
to run for presidency again in 2024 will
he declare his candidature will he
throws hat in the ring
and what else could happen that's the
question right
into that
um about Donald Trump and his
one second I am
give me a second please I will get back
into it right away
once I can resolve the issue of the lag
we see this lag once in a while why is
that
let's look into it one second
is it better
laggy laggy
come on
I think we're still lagging
we are still lagging or R is I'll be
fine now
we're fine now buffering buffering and
it's back on on track
I think it's fine now so the question
these two questions are about the
political future of Donald Trump Donald
Trump is right now the the uh
the number one leader you could say
in the Republican party and as of now
he's the most vocal vociferous leader
even though he has been banned from from
Twitter and other social media platforms
he has created his own social media
platform called Truth social and he is
very much active there and yes and he is
positioning himself or he is trying to
position himself as the uh
as the next Republican candidate for
presidency It is believed that he may
announce his 2024 presidency
presidential candidacy very soon maybe
as early as this coming week possibly
yeah so uh
so what did I what did I discuss on on
on the beer biceps podcast with with
ranveer I did say that what I said was
this I said that Trump was not allowed
to achieve anything
the entire political system seemed to be
you know it should it seemed like it was
stacked up against him and they did not
want him to be able to achieve anything
he wanted to build a wall they did not
allow him to build a wall he wanted to
do various other things and he was not
allowed to do any of those things right
he's in his even his own party seemed to
at times be you know at Cross purposes
with him and the reason for this is that
he is not a politician he's an outsider
an outsider who by who accidentally was
able to succeed in politics because it
was really because he's smart because
he's intelligent and he was able to you
know do what the other politicians could
not and he was able to connect with the
people and democracy actually worked for
once
that's what happened and uh so that was
a deal so he was not really allowed to
achieve any of the things he wanted to
achieve
uh now we have to understand what the
situation with Donald Trump is I spoke
about this yesterday as well what is
going to happen to Donald Trump and
what's going to happen to his movement
the Maga movement make America great
again we have to understand something
very clearly this
the current
see the question is about a red wave
there has been no red wave
everybody was anticipating a massive Red
Wave or red tsunami the Republicans will
swamp the Democrats and and gain a
crushing massive majority in the lower
house in the Upper House in the Senate
this has not happened it's still too
early to call if the Republicans do win
it's gonna be with a razor thin majority
very small tiny majority which is not
anywhere close to the 30 40 seats major
lead they were expecting to have and the
face of the campaign has been Donald
Trump he's the one big leader right now
in the Republican party and that's why
this is a big setback for Donald Trump
this essentially is the third straight
election in which Donald Trump has
failed to perform to expectations
through his expectations and to the
expectation of the Republican Party the
2018 midterm elections When Donald Trump
was president
in in those elections the Republicans
the the Democrats won the lower house
they gained more than 40 seats and the
Republicans were able to retain the
Senate but the the Democrats won the
house and there was a setback for Donald
Trump in 2018 when he was president in
2020 he lost the presidency
to Joe Biden any and and the Republicans
even won the how the the Senate so that
was a double setback for Donald Trump
and right now in the 2022 midterms there
is a possible perhaps slim majority in
the lower house and maybe in the Senate
it's still too early I would say to call
yeah
and the U.S elections are weird they go
on for days and days the last two three
seats are not announced for many days
and they are now still a little later
it's strange it's a very strange
electoral system
so these last three elections have been
setbacks for Donald Trump it's a
hat-trick of of setbacks he has come up
short each time which does not bode well
for him yeah
so Trump is still positioning himself as
the prime candidate for the 2022 2024
presidential election he may announce
his current candidacy soon yeah but
there are certain some Challengers on
the horizon there is the governor of
California or the governor of Florida
Ron DeSantis who could be uh who could
be uh Trump's top Challenger for the
2024 nomination and there's another guy
called um uh what's his name the
governor of Maryland Hogan Larry Hogan
who also is by in in some quarters is
being uh spoken about as a potential
Outsider who could challenge Donald
Trump yeah so that's what's happening uh
it's still too early to say if Donald
Trump will be able to uh first of all
secure the Republican candidacy for
president and even if he's able to do
that which is going to be difficult but
even if he's able to do that will he be
able to uh win the presidency in 2024 we
don't know so that the questions there
are multiple questions first of all
who's going to lead the Republicans in
2024 in the presidential race we don't
know Trump would want to do that he
really wants to know that he is most
likely going to announce very soon but
there are challenges to him because he
is not performed by him the second
question is who's going to lead the
Democrats in the next presidential race
Joe Biden is the sitting president it's
it's only into his first term so usually
I mean typically if the sitting
president would run for the next term
for a second term but Joe Biden is well
people are raising questions about him
and it's very visible that he is in
cognitive decline
so it's possible perhaps that he may not
run for president in 2024 will Kamala
Harris run for president well she's
turned out to be as big a disaster as as
Biden himself yeah she has not uh
exhibited any presidential
characteristics or any signs of
significant intelligence I would say so
that's a problem for the for the
Democrats themselves what's going to
happen yeah the other question is what
happens will will Biden become a lame
duck president or president only name if
the Republicans Republicans are able to
capture the lower house or maybe even
the Senate so we have all these
questions
upon us right now
so that's where we are uh there is no
guarantee that Donald Trump will be able
to secure the Republican candidacy in
2024 for the Pres in the presidential
race and even if he's able to we don't
quite know who's who if he is able to do
that who will be who will he be up
against there is a dearth of leadership
in the Democratic party will Hillary
Clinton come back for the 78th time as
to run for president we don't know uh
and there seems to be a leadership
vacuum in the in the the Republican
party as well I did speak about Ron
DeSantis and Larry Hogan there could be
some other people as well but yeah
this this uh there's nobody who like
stands out apart from Donald Trump he's
got this big personality he's been
president before he's a very successful
businessman so he still could be in
Prime position but we don't know but the
last three elections have been bad for
Donald Trump nobody can gloss over that
fact so this is the situation all these
factors are there right now it's still
not clear it's still two years away
maybe in six months Maybe by next week
we'll know perhaps if Donald Trump is is
going to throw his hat in the ring and
maybe in a few weeks maybe in a few
months we'll the situation will become a
little bit more clear as to what are Joe
Biden's plans what are Kamala Harris's
plans and who's gonna stand up against
Donald Trump within his own party to
secure the 2024 presidential nomination
this is the situation very complicated
uh it's it's if you're an outsider it's
fun to watch yeah so that's how it is I
mean people who love elections and who
are into the Electoral politics it's
great for them it's great fun for them I
look at it from from a geopolitical
angle so yeah I so that's what I'm
keeping an eye on it's it's obviously
important for the entire world what
happened in the US so we're gonna keep
watching this closely yes
okay
the next question is uh something I took
yesterday I spoke about this yesterday
but uh maybe in case some of you have
not seen it we will discuss this again
and the questions are why did Putin back
away from the kherson region could it be
a deception by him as you say nobody can
tell what's going on in his head could
there be a bigger plan at Play
Uh Russian army leaving Curson is a
defeat or is it a strategic Movement by
powerful and smart general Sergey
surovicin who led the Syria war and
proved his himself in the past
Russia confirmed that it pulled out of
the of kherson in Ukraine certainly that
doesn't indicate Russian defeat as shown
by the media but doesn't it open a path
to Crimea as for Ukraine as it would
become easier for Ukraine to launch an
offensive like the one in which they
blew up a section of the Crimean Bridge
these are the questions so we do know
that the Russians are withdrawing in the
are in the process of withdrawing from
Carson or have perhaps withdrawn
entirely we're still not quite sure
let's go to the map and see where is
Harrison yes
uh just give me a second I'm gonna put
the map on the screen and lead you all
to the region of Interest right now the
region that we are discussing her son
map here we are map is here
so we know where India is we go
westwards west west west uh temporary
Nation Afghanistan Iran Iraq turkey and
north of turkey we have the Black Sea
and north of the Black Sea we have
Ukraine Nova Rosia Ukraine whatever you
want to call it now where is Herson
herzon is in the south of Ukraine this
here is this the Port City no not the
port city but it's quite close to the
Black Sea it's the city of Harrison it
sits on the right bank or the West Bank
of the Great River niper
the diaper river is the I think the
fourth largest European river and it's
uh this river which on which the city of
cave is also founded
is also the name of an oblast or
province which is one of the four
provinces that Russia recently annexed
after its referendums and people have
yeah
and they annexed these uh the Russians
annexed these four provinces which means
that they became part of Russia they
call it reunification uh others would
call it annexation depends on your
perspective uh but it's now officially
from the Russian perspective become part
of Russian territory it's been reunified
with Russia which means it comes under
the Russian nuclear umbrella and I had
speculated that maybe that could cause
problems if somebody makes a move on
Russian territory it may be a red line
that the Russians do not want anybody to
cross and that could lead to nuclear
conflict with clearly clearly not the
case the Russians are withdrawing from
the northern and western part of the
Naper River they're withdrawing from
that part of her son Province what does
it mean let's let's look at a different
image to make things a little clearer
uh Let's do let's take a look at a
different image of
the same region uh it's a little small
let me begin it a little nah I think
this is fine okay so now we can see
where Herson is you can see the the
Northern
the western region and west of the river
that we're talking about that's where
the Russians are withdrawing from or uh
have withdrawn from what does it mean
what does it mean what does it indicate
does it indicate that Russia is losing
is this a disaster setback in the
beginning of the end for Russia does it
mean the tide has turned
is that what's happening does it mean
that Mr Putin has lost face he is is
this is is this indicative of a loss of
prestige and loss of reputation for Mr
Putin does it mean that they're going to
be Knives Out in Russia for Mr Putin
because leaders cannot fail leaders are
not allowed to fail in Russia
or how should India interpret this how
should Russia interpret this how should
the world these are the questions these
are the questions that we are dealing
with these are the questions that we are
grappling with right
so there are a number of possibilities
so we have we don't know what's
happening because we don't have we're
not pretty to the to the classified
information and the thought process
that's going on behind the scenes in the
Russian top leadership in the in the
armed forces first of all we have to
understand this
these decisions see we don't understand
that Mr Putin is not a military
commander
so he oversees military activities but
he doesn't decide exactly what happens
he has a grand
a plan for for Russia for the future of
Russia
and then the military its job is to
carry out
strategic Maneuvers tactical Maneuvers
Grand strategic campaigns in military
theaters to make Mr Putin's vision
uh become a reality to make it a reality
so when the military when the Russian
military does certain things it is
approved by Mr Putin but the tactics and
strategies are typically decided by the
top leadership of the military in
consideration with Mr Putin
so there are three or four possibilities
one possibility why is Russia
withdrawing from this part of Herson and
and giving up the city of kherson
does this does this mean they are losing
so one possibility and this is the least
likely possibility this first
possibility is that this is a nasty trap
that the Russians are setting for NATO
so what we are witnessing in Ukraine is
a proxy war it is between Russia and
NATO Ukraine is just the tool that NATO
is using uh Ukraine is being supplied
with essentially unlimited uh quantities
of arms ammunition and whatnot and the
ukrainians are waging Total War they're
throwing unlimited numbers of men into
the meat grinder of the war and so on
so one possibility is that Russia is
laying a nasty trap for NATO they will
withdraw they will induce the enemy to
come into this region and then maybe
they will do something nasty to them
yeah so this is a tried and tested
tactic in Warfare you know the false
retreat
so that is one possibility I think it's
the least likely possibility but we
should keep that in mind you know from
the this is the logic of strategy so
this is the least likely possibility the
second possibility
which is somewhat more likely is that
there are diplomatic negotiations going
on see diplomacy happens behind the
scenes diplomacy always happens in
secret it's only when an agreement is
reached that diplomatic statements are
made publicly especially between
adversaries and enemies so maybe there
are secret negotiations going on along
through back channels between Russia and
the West between Russia and NATO and
maybe
there is talk of a ceasefire Maybe yeah
maybe there is talk of a ceasefire and
maybe that ceasefire could fructify
could be finalized during the G20 Summit
or maybe after the G20 Summit soon after
perhaps maybe so in that case if there
is some such secret negotiations
happening through back through
diplomatic back channels then maybe one
of the prerequisites for a ceasefire is
that Russia gave up some token territory
maybe the Hearthstone the Hearthstone
City and north of the west of the Naper
River in exchange for the uh for NATO
agreeing to process fire that is a
hypothetical possibility I am not aware
of what's really happening I am just
saying that this could be a possibility
this is more likely than Russia setting
a trap for NATO so the Trap theory is
the least likely Theory the least likely
possibility higher than that there is
more probability of this being some kind
of a prerequisite for an impending
ceasefire
yeah so you do this and then we will
finalize the ceasefire that could be the
deal possibly
all right here we go once again
do I
one second let me fix this it's
okay I think we are yeah we're back
so the second possibility is that there
could be
an impending ceasefire and this is a
prerequisite for that the third
possibility
is that uh this is indeed a setback for
Russia
yeah
I think it's it's working fine now yeah
so the third possibility is that this is
indeed a setback for Russia their
military has been forced to withdraw
from this place and maybe they want to
regroup in the southern part
of the river and stay there for the
winter and play the long game so the
long game could last one years to one
year two years you know the conflict
would drag on for a long time so these
are the three possibilities that I can
think of in case the Russians have been
driven back
because of superior uh military
activities from Ukraine and NATO
in that case let's go back to the image
to to to to to to to see the image yes
let's go let's take a look at the image
so in case the Russians have actually
been militarily driven back by force and
they have been forcibly evicted from
west of the river
in that case what we will witness most
likely is that the Ukrainian forces or
NATO forces are going to try and cross
the river themselves and try to make a
move on Crimea itself and they are the
Crimea the province of Crimea is I
believe already in range of Ukraine's
long-range artillery so we could witness
bombardment artillery bombardment of
Crimea of the Crimea region and we could
possibly witness the the NATO forces
trying to cross the river and try to
liberate the whole of the Harrison
Province so in case this is a military
setback for Russia then we will see this
happening very soon
so if this happens then we know that if
the Russians have actually lost this
part through military force
if this is a secret negotiation secret
agreement then we will soon possibly see
a ceasefire so that will validate the
second theory but this is a a
prerequisite for a ceasefire and if
there is a disaster for Ukraine in the
next coming days in in Carson then it
could validate the theory that this was
a nasty trap set by the Russians so
these are the three possibilities this
is what I discussed yesterday is we
still have don't we still don't have
more clarity on the situation I will
keep monitoring the situation because it
is of of importance enough interest to
all of us yes so I'm Gonna Keep
monitoring this but this is where we are
so I hope this makes things a little
little clearer for everybody this is
where we are right now next question
okay bye bye says will brics be the next
U.N and Bobby says this was always about
the New World Order the NV NWO and the
challenge of the old order uh bis
Britain was international monetary fund
World Bank central banks Reserve
currency Etc all these systems created
by the west west 70 years ago one is
Bitcoin the other is bricks and there
might be more out there what do you
think
brics is definitely a challenge to the
existing whims based world order the
rules-based world order the imperial
system that has been constructed by the
West which essentially means the regime
that is run out of Washington DC in the
Pentagon yes this was all created in
1945 with the Bretton Woods agreement
which made the U.S dollar the world's
Reserve currency everybody agreed to
this and that's been the financial the
backbone of the financial Financial
system ever since
so uh bricks so this is what we called
the the old order yeah the the U.S
rules-based rules-based world order
whatever you want to call it right uh
brics is definitely a challenge to this
so bricks could represent like Bobby
says the new world order or an
aspirational new world order a
bifurcation of the system a new system
which will exist initially in parallel
which will attempt to exist in parallel
to the U.S imperial system yes
um yeah so it is definitely that and
it's a it's a it's a dangerous thing to
do because you know if you try to
challenge the the giant the mighty
superpower there's gonna be retaliation
there's gonna be massive retaliation so
the brics nations are going to have to
trade very carefully lots of Nations
want to join brics the Saudis want to
join brics that is a very
very audacious and very dangerous move
by Muhammad Salman because his nation
was essentially created by the British
to to further British geopolitical and
Imperial Ambitions yes and then it was
after the British seeded uh see seeded
the crown to the Americans the Saudis
became essentially a U.S client State
and the house of Saud owes its existence
and continued uh rain rule Prosperity
whatever to the West
so attempting signaling its intention to
join brics is a very dangerous thing do
from Muhammad Wilson's perspective but
he has done that well kudos to him and I
wish him well uh one
we know history we know what happens to
uh
uh to clients of the U.S who who tried
to break free of the U.S so we have seen
various such examples in various parts
of the world one such example which is
not very old is that of Saddam Hussein
Saddam Hussein we know what happened to
him so Mr Muhammad bin Salman needs to
be very very careful yeah so all of this
is definitely an attempt to set up a
parallel system
a more fair system of system that is
more Equitable perhaps
and uh you know it will give
it will offer an alternative to
countries that want to break free of the
imperial system so this is definitely
that Bitcoin isn't is an attempt to do
that as well you know to break free of
the hegemony
of the centralized Banks which control
the money so your money essentially is
owned by them that's how it is yeah so
if you're Bitcoin it's entirely
decentralized it's permissionless
and uh it offers you actual Freedom
um
not ethereum not other cryptocurrencies
but Bitcoin does but now we have seen
that crypto is crashing it may be being
made to crash and uh yeah we are seeing
these these tussles being you know the
initial initial jousting happening right
now
uh in the coming years this will most
likely intensify
so yes the brics is the New World Order
it's an attempt to create a new world
order or a parallel world order a
bifurcation of the global system you
know in which everything will will
become bifurcated the financial system
the supply chains and so much more
there's so much more energy materials
agriculture Transportation
infrastructure uh manufacturing like I
said Supply chains and so many other
things could become bifurcated if Brix
is able to uh succeed So Many Nations
seem to find it attractive Algeria wants
to join bricks Algeria is one of the
major oil I mean gas supplies of the
world uh Indonesia May apply to join
bricks next week during the G20 Summit
turkey seems to have expressed its uh
desire to perhaps explore being a part
of brics Argentina and many other
nations yeah so it's an interesting time
so this is all definitely an attempt to
create a parallel system parallel
New World Order and let's see how it
goes let us see how it goes
right once again we are buffering why
does this happen and it is so unknown
man
let me
permanent solution to this but I think
it's getting better
yes it's better
okay the next question is also about
bricks it's from India's perspective
Gotham Anand India is in groups like The
SEO the Shanghai cooperation
organization brics Etc and at the same
time we are also part of groupings such
as the quad this Balancing Act foreign
policy of India while also focusing on
our interests is feasible and giving
good results of now do you think it is
practical in the long run as India's
stature Rises geopolitically till what
time can we manage to be a part of both
the opposite camps of global geopolitics
this is a good question so India is
indeed a member of the Shanghai
cooperation organization which is a
grouping that's essentially led by the
Chinese and also the Russians so India
China Russia are part of the SEO other
nations as well
brics is also the core group is India
Russia China Plus South Africa plus
Brazil and many other nations want to
join so India is part of this
alternative grouping which is an
alternative to the west to the Western
hegemony but India is also part of the
quad
so why is India doing this it's doing it
for to safeguard its own
National interest because China is a
major threat to India China has been a
major threat to India since the 1950s
when it uh forcibly occupied and a next
Tibet as long as India and China share a
common border whether it's demarcated or
not India China are going to be
adversaries and Rivals especially when
the border is on demarcated and
especially when China has become so
massively powerful economically you know
uh five times the size of India's
economy right now that's what the GDP is
like approximately five times the size
and obviously that military will also be
massive they have a lot of other issues
geopolitically their military is not
entirely concentrated on the India Tibet
border it's it's spread out but yes
China is a major concern it's India's
number one threat and because of that
India is has chosen has opted to be a
part of the Quad grouping which is
essentially India and the US and a
couple of uh U.S satellites which is
Australia and Japan yes
so uh yes and India also has excellent
not excellent but good relations with
the US
um India is giving what we what we would
call issue based cooperation to the us
we are cooperating fully from the
economic development perspective and the
technology and all that but we are
giving issue based cooperation uh when
it comes to strategic strategic Affairs
and geopolitics so that's the kind of uh
relationship India and the U.S have
nowadays we have seen that the US is
once again supporting Pakistan you know
that is a direct threat to India yeah
you support India's number two adversary
militarily you're essentially investing
in India's future you know in bleeding
India in the future so that's the kind
of relationship we have with the US now
you cannot and obviously we know that
India has been purchasing
arms systems like the S 400 system like
submarines
Etc from the Russians from Russia
various aircraft many other things we
may even be in on the verge of
purchasing heavy strategic bombers from
Russia that's what one hears yeah that's
what the you know the Grapevine tells us
so India is doing all this the Americans
are obviously not pleased about this but
they gave India the katsa waiver where
it can comes to the S 400 system if
India goes ahead and purchase the
purchases the Russian uh strategic heavy
bomber the white swan bomber that could
be a whole different thing so India is
doing this very delicate Balancing Act
vis-a-vis the US and the East the East
is India China Russia essentially yep
this is Impractical in the long run in
the long run India will have to choose a
camp
will it be on the side of Russia and
China China is an adversary brics is
essentially
unviable in the long term as long as
India and China have this adversarial
relationship
the only way India and China will not
have an adversarial relationship for
some time is if the border is demarcated
the India Tibet border is demarcated
until that happens
it's unviable
uh yes FBI seems to have joined the chat
somebody is saying
damn this
so we are buffering once again let me
try and overcome that
buffering buffering buffering
it's not better yet
okay uh yes people are giving me
technical advice to set the bit rate
correctly
CIA in chat
I think it's getting better it's getting
better
it's getting better it's better now
so like I was saying it is
like I was saying bricks
is not a viable Coalition in the long
run if India and China remain at
groceries and there is as as far as we
see right now there is no major move or
steps being taken for India and China to
resolve the Border issue
so in that case it would be kind of
unwise for India to throw its lot with
bricks especially when China is the
major economy in bricks that's dangerous
but once again when it comes to the US
in the west they are now favoring
Pakistan over India so it it doesn't
make a lot of sense for India to throw
its lot in with the us as well
so that is the conundrum The Dilemma
that India is facing right now I would
say that India needs to
to put it put its head down and work on
the economy India has to anyhow
somehow anyhow ensure that there are the
next 10 20 years are years of Peace
there is no major conflict no major war
yeah do The Balancing Act anyhow and
ensure that you reach at least uh 10
trillion dollars of GDP annual GDP once
you do that uh India will become a whole
different beast and it will be difficult
for even a nation like China to think
about uh needling India or try to trying
to you know
so yeah it's it's a current run for
India bricks
is I mean we would like to see a
parallel world order a new world order a
different set of rules as compared to
the old you know the Legacy uh world
order the Imperial World Order of the
U.S the so-called rules-based uh system
the UN system and all that we would like
to see a new thing come up but as long
as India and China have this
relationship bad relationship it's not
going to be long-term viable it's viable
in the long term so yeah that's where we
are and right now there are no right
answers
right now there are no right answers so
India has to essentially
not rely on anybody nobody's gonna come
and save India if something goes wrong
India is essentially on its own all
nations are on their own some Nations
have their groupings like the U.S has a
bunch of like 50 60 Versailles states
that it can order to do whatever it
wants
uh the Chinese have Pakistan they had
Pakistan Pakistan is now in the U.S Camp
so the Chinese have South Korea and they
were trying to bribe various Nations but
nobody trusts China anymore
China and Russia have this transactional
relationship of which is kind of a
Cooperative relationship for now but
Russia does not trust China and neither
does China trust Russia so brics is
India and Russia have a reasonable
amount of trust so as long as China is
in bricks it's it's a problem in China
refuses to behave China itself has
Imperial Ambitions of its own
so yeah that is the problem which we are
in right now from India's perspective
and time will tell how it goes the only
thing for India is to rise India has to
anyhow ensure that it rises economically
and stays peaceful for the next 10 years
at least yeah one could deal with
Pakistan in a variety of ways but there
should be no war with China or any other
major Nations for minimum the next 10
years then India will be in a good
position to
set its own rules so that's that's the
situation
okay summer says in response to Israel's
plan to open two agricultural centers of
excellence in Jammu and Kashmir
pakistan-backed terror group has warned
of attacks targeting Israeli Assets in
the union territory despite India U.S
deteriorating deteriorating ties India
Israel Defense cooperation to increase
is increasing considering a rise in
Terror threats
notably there is a change in the Israeli
leadership again yes there is a change
in the Israeli leadership of Mr
Netanyahu and his Coalition have won the
elections and Mr Netanyahu has been been
given about I don't know 30 days or so
to form a government so that's what we
are witnessing in Israel the Israelis
have the same kind of Westminster
parliamentary Westminster inspired
parliamentary system that we have in
India which is an offshoot which is a
copy essentially in in a way of the
British parliamentary system which
inherently is in unstable democratic
system you know leadership can change
anytime and all that so that's what
Israel is dealing with now yes so Mr
Netanyahu seems to be back in the saddle
he seems to be back in control possibly
of Israel of the leadership and yeah we
we have uh India Israel cooperation
India Israel is planning to open two
centers of excellence agricultural in in
Kashmir Jamul Kashmir and the pakistanis
are making you know threats and all that
yeah
so the question is will India Israel
ties keep on improving and remain strong
and India Israel Defense cooperation
other things as well will this remain
stronger despite deteriorating India U.S
ties
and the implicit assumption or implicit
question in this is that Israel's
foreign policy is a reflection or
extension of U.S foreign policy which it
is to a large extent through no fault of
Israel's
Israel is a small nation it was
recreated uh
it was recreated uh when was it 1948 or
thereabouts yeah in the 1940s
and it's been under siege essentially
from its neighbors ever since
um so the Israelis they have a
significant diaspora in the U.S I think
the number of Jews in the U.S is seven
or eight million there's a lot of
support to Israel from there
uh and Israel this entire the entire
situation in the Middle East let's take
a look at the map of the Middle East
just you know uh for clarity let's take
a look at the map of the Middle East and
see where Israel is
uh right so this is the Middle East and
this here is Israel on the eastern coast
of the Mediterranean Sea as you can see
it has a lot of adversaries around it
Egypt Jordan Saudi Saudi Arabia Syria
Lebanon
and not far away you have turkey and so
on
so all the Arab nations in the in Turkey
but yeah so Israel is has always been
under siege ever since it was recreated
reformed yeah uh so Israel the entire
situation in the Middle East the
straight-line Nations artificial Nations
all that it has been designed or created
by the West in such a way that the
entire region stays essentially
permanently in turmoil in Conflict the
Middle East has been in crisis for
decades essentially ever since the end
of the second world war more or less one
conflict one problem after the other and
it's it's been designed to be that way
now Israel to a large extent its foreign
policy is indeed an extension of U.S
foreign policy it was LA to a large
extent that is true but the Israelis do
not see themselves as a Visa state of
the U.S the Israelis see them Israel as
a nation sees itself in a way like India
sees itself as a civilizational state
Israel is way older than the United
States
Israel is I would say slightly more than
3000 years old if you look at the the
oldest records of the Jewish people I
think it's it's found in the in
an inscription in Egypt in one of the
pharaohonic inscriptions in Egypt that
dates back to slightly more than 3000
years so the Jewish people have been
around for a long time at least three
thousand years and they lived in this
region which is currently which is now
called Israel yeah that's it's there's a
whole history behind it but then the
Romans destroyed Israel they destroyed
Judea they forced lots of Jewish people
out of Israel they that became the
wandering Jewish diaspora but settled
down in parts of Europe and then there
was the the Islamic expansion into this
region the ottoman expansion
um there was Saladin and so many people
because of which the the Jewish people
were forced to essentially
uh leave this region so for the longest
time there was no Israel and then the
nation was recreated in the first half
of the 20th century
so Israel has a long history the the
Jewish people uh are very uh proud of
that
and because of that they have their own
vision of what the future should be like
and that is not the same essential
that's not entirely the same as what the
U.S would like them to be whenever the
Democrats are in power there's a lot of
conflict between Israel and the U.S the
relationship between Barack Obama Obama
and uh Bibi Netanyahu was very strained
it was a very cold and and uh you know
it was not a good relationship so
whenever the Democrats in power there
are problems within between in the in
the Israeli U.S relationship so the
Israelis they do
conform to to U.S dictats in a variety
of ways from the foreign policy
perspective but they also have to to
some extent an independent foreign
policy and
India and Israel the national interests
of these two Nations they converged to a
significant extent and that's why the
Israelis they would like the nation to
exist for the for the longest time and
for that to happen they need
strong allies
and cooperation they read cooperation
from Nations like India it would be best
it would be good for both Nations that
way you know so um so despite I would
say that despite the uh deteriorating
India U.S relationship I think the India
Israel relationship will remain strong
will remain positive
and it's going to remain a good
Cooperative relationship that's what I
see unless the US decides to go ahead
and totally arm twist Israel in which
case the Israelis may have to capitulate
but as long as the Americans don't try
to arm twist the Israelis as long as
that doesn't happen the india-israel
relationship will most likely remain
strong uh and and cooperative
so that's what I
believe will happen but obviously time
will tell if the India U.S relationship
becomes so bad that the Americans Force
Israel to stop cooperating with India
then things may change but unless that
happens which seems to be somewhat
unlikely right now uh things will remain
good between India and Israel and that's
what I hope
foreign
Heartland is occupied by Russia then why
is it not a superpower
okay so this is about the macinders
Heartland theory uh which is something
which I spoke about I think during the
last episode of the Indian interest so
let's take a look at the map and
understand what this is so according to
the uh British academic geostrategist
whatever you want to call him
mcinder according to him uh
the world island is made up of you
essentially Eurasia yes Eurasia and uh
the Heartland is the region from the
volca Volga to to essentially uh the
youngjae river which means it is the
region that has traditionally been part
of the Russian Empire which was then
later the USSR in which is now mostly
Russia yes so this was a theory put
forth by Halford mackender who uh wrote
it in an article I think in the very
early 20th century so we have the world
Island and then you have the interlinked
continents of which is the interlinked
continents of Europe and Asia
uh you have Africa and then you have the
offshore islands like the British
Islands the island of Japan and all that
and the outlying islands are North
America South America and Oceania which
is uh Australia and all that so
according to mcinder the pivot area the
most important area in the world is the
Heartland which is from the Volga to the
youngster Rivers yes the Himalayas to
the Arctic that that part of Eurasia it
is what is currently Russia more or less
and this region contains about 50 of the
world's resources raw minerals raw
materials minerals petroleum products
oil gas Metals agriculture everything
you need to indefinitely sustain a
nation and a large military and this
Heartland is protected by
it is protected uh from C Power by the
ice in the north the ice in the north
this region and by mountains and deserts
in the South so it is very well
protected and makinder said that whoever
rules Eastern Europe commands the
Heartland and whoever commands the
Heartland commands the world Island and
whoever rules the world Highland Island
commands the world so the key to the
Heartland is Eastern Europe and the key
to Eastern Europe is Ukraine and that is
the source of the conflict that we're
witnessing NATO was trying to expand
into Ukraine yes so this is the
Heartland rimland theory in this rimland
Theory as well so China and India are
rimland powers according to this yeah so
China is a rimland or Rim world powers
[Music]
um
so the question is the Heartland is
occupied by Russia so why is it not a
superpower well go back 20 30 years the
USSR was a superpower go back a century
before that the Russian Empire was a
superpower it was the most it was the
major power for the longest time for a
very long time in in Europe until the
the ascendancy of the British Empire
so it is not enough
to Simply control the Heartland it is
not enough see in the Heartland you have
access to all the resources you have
access to energy like oil and and
petroleum products and gas you have
energy you have access to all kinds of
materials you have lots of great fertile
agricultural land and you have this
immense territory so this is what the
Heartland gives you but that's not
enough to become a superpower you need
Transportation you need to construct
roads Railways you need all the entire
Transportation infrastructure you need
the finance Network you need
manufacturing unit Supply chains you
need to invest in engineering and
technology in the research and
development you need to invest in
world-class education system fundamental
scientific research you need to have a
culture of innovation you need to have a
culture of meritocracy you need the
demography needs to be taken care of
there has to be social cohesion there
needs to be pride in the nation and its
culture there has to be a strong
National Vision you need a very powerful
leader ship strong leadership you need
political stability and to safeguard all
of this you need a powerful military
that's what makes a superpower
so the United States
for the longest time it was it was occup
it was it was inhabited by the Native
Americans they did not create a
superpower but the the
Europeans the Anglo-Saxons they
conquered the the North American
continent they got rid of the natives
more or less and they created the
superpower so it's not enough to have
the territory you have to build all this
on top of the territory so when this
USSR broke up in the 1990s old all that
I spoke about was was absent the
transportation infrastructure was there
but the finance the economy became very
bad right the political leadership was
terrible Boris yelts in the drunkard
yeah there was no political stability
there was the the leadership was weak
yeah the the economy became I mean it it
crumbled when when your economy is not
strong you can't have a powerful
military you can't have a great
education system you can't have uh you
know research and development in Science
and Technology and Engineering in
Innovation all those things so that's
what went wrong and now the Russians are
trying to recreate that so it is not
enough to occupy the Heartland you have
to build on top of it you know you to
create this wonderful top of the line
system only then will you have the
ability to potentially transform
yourself into a superpower I hope that
answers the question
ayush
suhas says
when I was searching about the Heartland
theory I also came across the rimland
theory won't having control over a
majority of the rimland from Iran to
parts of Thailand me India's best
interest since we dream of being a
superpower
um once again let's take a look at the
map so the written land is this entire
region for the region of Japan no Japan
is the outlying islands one of the
outlying islands but China uh southeast
Asia in India this is all the rimland
yes so uh the rimland according to
makender is vulnerable to the Heartland
power and the ocean power which is U.S
and NATO
so it's because it's exposed to both
these uh both these major Powers anyhow
that's the theory now
the Dreamland I mean if you look at
China versus India China is encircled by
the three Island chains one island chain
is the uh Japanese Islands in Taiwan
then you have the Philippines and the
other islands and then you have the
Mariana's another the third Argentine
there are three Island chains that
prevent that essentially shackle China
and prevent it from becoming a major
Naval power and these Island trains are
controlled by the U.S when it comes to
India there is no such constraint
right so India is a rembrand power India
has access India occupies this
god-gifted commanding position over the
entire Indian Ocean region India has
always been a maritime power for the
past 10 000 years yes
so I think India should really focus on
Naval power
and or Naval aerial power as well India
has these Unsinkable aircraft carriers
the Andaman and nicobar islands and the
lakshadweep islands they potentially
also in the future could have a very
excellent mutually beneficial
relationship with Sri Lanka as well in
the future
we have the Maldives as well with which
we could have the same kind of
relationship so India is potentially a
great rimland power if it can create the
economy that can sustain a major
military that can sustain its interests
its strategic interests in this area we
uh don't need to occupy Iran in parts of
Thailand like you're mentioning I mean
India has always been a major power
without doing that uh India in the past
did indeed occupy the entirety of
Southeast Asia up to the Philippines
once as far as we know in its history
which was about a thousand years ago
under the rule of the great Chola Empire
there are rajaraj and rajendra Chola but
uh
you don't have to conquer and occupy
places like Iran or nations like Iran
and Thailand all you need to do is to
have a good relationship with them a
good mutually respectful mutually
beneficial relationship in that case we
can have access to that those parts of
the rimland as well
so uh you don't need to have control
over it but you need to have
access to it because of a good
relationship with with those Nations so
yes you are right I see does India dream
of being a superpower lots of people I
mean in the comments I see it every
almost every day when is India becoming
a superpower so yes Indians are now
aspiring the Indian population
especially the youngsters are now
aspiring uh to see the aspiration is to
see India becoming a superpower soon
maybe in the next 20 years maybe
definitely within our lifetimes yes
does the Indian leadership
want to see India being a superpower
maybe maybe not we don't know we there
are no pronouncements as such from the
leadership and it is always wise not to
uh not to not to talk about your
long-term Ambitions and aspirations and
hopes
uh but India historic the India's
historical position has been of the
world's largest economy for the past 10
000 years essentially
and if you look at the study of the past
2000 years or from from the uh what's
his name
uh Angus medicine right
so he published his his very influential
uh study of the world's economy in the
past two thousand years in India until
the 1700s was the world's largest
economy it uh accounted for at least a
third of the entire world's GDP right
and in the past it would have been even
more than that so India historically has
been always the number one economic
power
and at times it's been the world's major
military power as well from various in
in various times
for instance during the the kushan
Empire later during
um the Gupta Empire the karakota Empire
the Chola Empire and so on and so forth
so there have been times when India and
obviously the mauryan Empire as well
so India is a potential superpower India
is definitely already to some extent a
great power one of the three or four
great thoughts in the world maybe the
three great powers
and in the future it could be a
superpower if India plays its cards
right and I would say that the key to
becoming a superpower in the next 20 to
50 years is to focus
on the maritime element on the Sea on
the rim India is a remland power India
commands the entire Indian Ocean so
India should leverage that God gifted
position that it has in that if it does
then so India needs to invest in a
powerful navy
India needs to develop the unsinkable
aircraft carriers which is the under
money covered islands and the luxury
violence and India should also invest in
a powerful Coast Guard in in a powerful
and extensive
uh Merchant Navy which can serve a dual
purpose that's what the Chinese are
doing so learn from our adversaries
so yeah what's the answer
okay this is a question I've not taken
for a while but I see it every single
day people ask me this question every
day
our defense minister said that we will
soon acquire the regions of Pakistan
occupied Kashmir is there any chance of
China involving in the support of
Pakistan militarily the second question
is Mr Raj is not saying indirectly spoke
about
taking back P okay
including this in mind if we see India
is building an air base near the
Pakistan border there's an accidental
fire of the of the brahmots into
Pakistani territory
and there are Air Force exercises
currently happening near the Pakistan
border is the park India war about to
happen in the next 10 years for Pok and
will we really take back to you okay
soon why did the Army announce that are
they really going to attack should
shouldn't they be keeping it a secret
whatever plans you have you should
always keep them a secret and whatever
you talk about should not give away your
real plans
so what did Mr rajna think about defense
minister say he said that poke will come
have some patience it will come soon
enough that's what he said he did not
give a timeline he did not he did not
announce that next week we are
launching and launching uh Liberation uh
exercise or Liberation maneuver of Pok
no such thing has been announced he said
have patience poke will return to India
soon enough that's what he said it
is a general statement
if you actually are planning to do that
you never ever announce it
which means there are no plans currently
to make a move and be okay please
understand that it's not going to happen
next week next month or next year if I'm
not mistaken or maybe sometimes you do a
double Bluff in cricket if you want to
bowl a bouncer you put a guy on the
Square leg boundary and make it look
like the to the batsman like you know
you're in a bowl of Yorker and then you
actually bowl a bouncer so yeah there
could be a bluff there could be a Double
Bluff that could be a triple buff we
don't know
but I don't see India making a move to
take back and reunify be okay with India
in the immediate future
but obviously it is definitely
on the cards in the medium to long term
it's gonna happen it's gonna happen
nobody no power no force in the world
can stop this from happening from India
re-unifying Pok with India and
liberating the rest of the
Pakistani is a temporary Pakistani
process from the tyranny of the
Pakistani army it's going to happen yeah
uh so yes we are building air bases near
the Pakistan because we should we we do
it because we can and because we should
so we are doing it it doesn't
necessarily mean anything yeah uh there
has been an accidental firing of the
brahmos missile which inadvertently went
into Pakistani airspace and crashed into
Pakistani territory which was an
accident you know it happens sometimes a
nuclear-capable supersonic cruise
missile
and there are Air Force exercises which
will which happen regularly
you go to any water area you will see
fighter planes buzzing around its
supersonic speeds Sonic booms grow
dropping Sonic booms everywhere it
doesn't mean that we're going to
imminently uh retake poke
um so yeah so uh this is just a general
statement obviously it creates a lot a
lot of excitement in various quarters of
the Indian population various parts of
the Indian population it when it happens
it will be very exciting it will be very
fast
but it's not happening soon as far as I
can see
uh will the Chinese get involved in
supporting Pakistan militarily when
India reacquires poke
it depends on a whole lot of factors
if we do it now the Chinese will most
likely want to get involved
they will most likely want to get
involved and so these are the
calculations these are the different
parameters you need to look at before
you make any move
when you launch a military operation
ideally you want to launch the military
occupation when you are 100 certain of
winning
and when you are certain that your
casualties will be less you don't want
to take lots of casualties and you want
to win ideally you want to win without
fighting ideally you want to see
Pakistan
give up you okay voluntarily ideally
fighting without fighting like Bruce Lee
said
so that's the ideal situation
so as long as the China factor is there
as long as the U.S factor is that India
will not make a move on Pok India will
make its move
on Pok when the situation is
advantageous when the time is right and
that time is not right now right now the
U.S will not want India to take back be
okay because if we take back PUK we have
direct access to Afghanistan
then we can
have direct access to Central Asia
through Afghanistan that would be
extremely advantageous for Russia as
well
it would be great for Afghanistan as
that would not be great for the
long-term American
objectives in the region right
it would give Russia access to
to warm water ports in India which would
totally upend the world order in very
short time in a very short amount of
time so uh if India tries to take back
puke right now the Americans will try to
prevent that through variety of means
even the park is even the Chinese will
try to do that which is why now is not
the right time in my opinion obviously I
could be wrong and tomorrow we could see
PUK being liberated in which case I'll
eat my words but yeah that's what I
think right now it's it's a little early
for us to take back the okay but it will
happen sooner rather than later it will
happen
foreign
attempt on Mr Imran Khan during his long
march who do you think was behind this
assassination attempt and where do you
see Pakistan in the next 10 years
keeping in view the current political
and economic crisis and bye-bye says
what's your take on Imran Khan being
shot at or shot was that a false flag or
was it was it like like a real
assassination attempt
um do you think he is the one going to
prove the temporary Nation
okay
um who do I think was behind the
assassination attempt was this a false
flag operation or was it a genuine
assassination attempt
um it's hard to tell but see if you look
at what happened to Benazir Bhutto it
was a very similar kind of situation she
was doing this public rally and she was
shot and she was shot in the head by
somebody at all almost nearly Point
Blank rage somebody just walked up to
her and shot her in the head I think
there were multiple controls and then
there was a Bomb Blast as well to create
confusion
so um something similar seems to have
happened in the case of Mr Imran Khan
right now if
if you were a professional professional
assassin
you're not gonna miss from from close
range and if you if you're standing on
the ground and you're shooting at
fighting at somebody who's on a higher
at a higher level than you you're not
going to end up shooting the person in
the leg which kind of makes it look
fishy
that y was the only shot in the leg
I mean the the when a person you know
when when a person is shot in battle or
in any other situation the odds are that
that person will be shot in the Torso
the chest or in the abdomen because that
is the largest part of the body the arms
and legs are very much smaller targets
so if you're shot in that it is it's
kind of fishy it's like somebody wanted
to shoot you there only so that you
don't get
you know killed
typically if you're shot in the arm of
the leg you'll survive that you'll lose
blood and you may need an operation you
may need uh you know
corrective surgery to your bone or
whatever in case it is clipped but
overall it's not a fatal wound
so either this was a false flag
operation to make it look like somebody
wants to kill him and maybe to Garden of
sympathy for him that is one possible
scenario the other possibility is that
the the Assassin was an amateur and that
person or persons genuinely goofed up
and Mr Imran Khan got lucky these are
the two possibilities I don't know who
could be behind the assassination
attempt
obviously he was the for he is the
former prime minister he was evicted out
ousted which cannot happen without the
connivance and the approval of the
Pakistani deep state which is the isi
and the Army mainly the Army and the isi
you know and also the the uh the foreign
Ministry or whatever the bureaucracy the
permanent establishment
so it it uh Mr Imran Khan was removed
from power it this removal could only
have been done with the approval of the
Pakistani army isi and deep state
and we know the shift that's happened in
Pakistan
for the last decade or so they were
calling China their iron brother but now
we are seeing
uh Resurgence of interest in Pakistan
from the US
and the U.S has way deeper pockets and a
much bigger stick than the Chinese do
which means that Pakistan is now a
proper U.S vasal state all over again
so
so most likely the odds are that Mr
Imran Khan was removed from power at the
behest of the US it all happened after
his his visit to Russia on in in on the
same day that Mr Putin launched the
invasion of Ukraine which was very bad
Optics yeah
and maybe that was all done on purpose
to to make it easier for the pakistanis
to remove Imran Khan or whatever
so in case it is in it so in case the
Deep State the Army the isi views Mr
Imran Khan as a long-term threat to
their Ambitions and to their plans then
maybe they want to eliminate him that's
that's a possibility and maybe it's
being done at the behest of some foreign
powers also perhaps who knows so that is
one possibility the other possibility is
that this was some local disgruntled
element who wanted to kill Mr England
Khan maybe that person was an amateur or
maybe this was something done
by from from from
sources close to Mr Imran Khan himself
perhaps to perhaps Garner sympathy for
him among the Pakistani avam the
Pakistani janta the population these are
three possibilities that I can think of
I don't know which one is correct
um some possibilities uh have a higher
probability but we're not quite sure and
most likely we won't know but but he has
survived and good for him
good for him
so yeah and the other question is where
do I say Pakistan in the next 10 years
keeping in with the current political
and economic crisis see Pakistan was
created to divide the people of the
Indian subcontinent it was created by
the UK to further its geopolitical
long-term ambitions
and you that's what it was and once the
crown was passed on from the UK to the
U.S the U.S has used Pakistan to further
its geopolitical its geostrategic
objectives in the Indian subcontinent
region and overall in Eurasia
one trouble spot is the Middle East
which is permanently in crisis the other
trouble spot they have created the West
is the Indians abundant which is divided
artificially
and where all these tensions are
periodically inflamed so the
india-pakistan thing has always been
there since 1947 24 1948 right
so as long as these powerful Nations
essentially the us earlier was China as
long as the U.S sees Pakistan as a value
valuable asset
as long as that happens Pakistan will
continue to exist
if the U.S loses interest then maybe the
Chinese will take over so it's also
essentially Pakistan has been created by
foreign powers to divide India and it
has been propped up ever since the
various military dictatorships these
dictatorships have been propped up and
sustained by foreign powers
the moment foreign powers stop
sustaining Pakistan Pakistan will
implode the problem is it's it's a
nuclear armed state
we don't want to have a nuclear-armed
Somalia you know chaos that's the last
thing we want I think yeah so so that's
that's the situation so I think as long
as the U.S props up the pakistanis
Pakistan Will Survive will keep on
existing the people will survive somehow
in the Army in the isi and all the the
top brass will keep getting richer they
will buy properties in London in the U.S
they will send their children to study
there and they will have fat bank
accounts over there and when the time is
dead they will leave the country
so as long as the foreign Nations
foreign powers keep on propping up
Pakistan it will exist will this go on
for the next 10 years perhaps odds are
that Pakistan may not
survive 10 years like I've said so many
times I have nothing against the people
of Pakistan I wish them well I wish them
Prosperity I wish their children and
their descendants prosperity and and
safety but Pakistan is a terrorist
Nation
and this nation needs to be uh dealt
with appropriately hopefully without any
any military per military force without
any violence hopefully but yeah that's
what it is it's a terrorist Nation it's
been the epicenter of global terrorism
for the longest time since the 1980s at
least
so Pakistan needs to be dealt with maybe
it may last 10 years but uh its
long-term survival is highly highly
improbable
right
uh swastika says shouldn't Pakistani
Punjab and Sindh also be a part of India
as they were so before partition if
partition hadn't happened those areas
would have been part of India but you
but I say that those two regions should
be independent like Balochistan why do I
say this shouldn't Pakistani Punjab and
sin be part of India look
Pakistan
is an integral part of India it's always
been part of India for the longest time
10 000 plus years in the future it will
again become part of India
but right now it is not practical even
if Pakistan breaks up
even if Pakistan breaks up right now it
is not practical to reintegrate those
paths
like Sindhu in Balochistan and Pakistan
Punjab Etc with India right now why is
that because the population for the past
three four five six Generations has been
totally radicalized and they've been
taught
to hate India and Indian culture they
have been fed this Venom from the time
they are born so if you look at a
hundred pakistanis I would say 90 of
them would have this strong hatred
and any and animosity
very strong animosity towards India and
it's not possible to reintegrate
people with that mindset so once
whenever it happens that Pakistan
is is is
balkanized and Sindh becomes independent
Punjab becomes independent becomes
independent maybe go back to Afghanistan
once this happens there once the the
evil Shadow of the isi and the Pakistan
Army is is taken away
from the poor hapless suffering people
of Pakistan then it will take another
three four generations for for that
mindset to perhaps go away
only then can we reintegrate
those regions
with uh with India
so it will happen in the long run but it
will it is not advisable to do it
immediately
so there should be a cooling off period
maybe
50 years or so and and then things may
be better you know
so that's why those regions need to be
independent for some time at least
obviously synth Punjab Balochistan
although even Afghanistan of course was
part of India let's talk about the
region of Pakistan right now Sindhi is
obviously an integral part of India
India is incomplete without the Sindhu
River
the Sindhu river is one of the two great
ancient rivers of India one of the three
four one of the
four or five great ancient rivers of
India which were at the heart of Indian
civilization one is the ganga the other
is the yamuna the other two of the
Saraswati and the Sindhu the Saraswati
no longer is with us she chose to leave
that's a choice but the Sindhu India is
incomplete without the sindhurima the
Indus River some parts of it do flow
through India in Northern India in
ladakh ETC very beautiful River but yes
the whole of the river has to eventually
be
returned to the fold of India it will
happen but not yet it is not practical
if Pakistan breaks up to immediately you
reunify those regions
of those territories with India it will
take time we have to be practical
okay what is this from um
okay the question is I'd like to hear
your comments on the great nicobar
development project in terms of security
economy
environmental impact impact on
indigenous tribes
um that's in Thai
so uh what is this great nicobar
development project let's take a I mean
I I hope you all know where the nicobar
islands are but the great nicobar island
is you have the Andaman and nicobar
Islands over here the archipelago and
the great nicobar Island I believe is
this one
this is little Andaman
okay it's here
this is the great nicobar Island so the
northern islands are the Andaman Islands
in the southern Islands other nicobar
islands and this one here is the great
nicobar Island which is the southern uh
southernmost part of India it's about
200 or so kilometers away from Indonesia
which means Indonesia is our neighboring
country in case you don't know so there
is going to be this massive not massive
but a significant uh development project
on this island now let's take a look at
a news article that tells us a little
bit more about that let's remove this
from the screen and let's put up that
news article where is it
okay this is it uh let me put it up on
the screen and then let's discuss what's
happening there it's a very important
project
so environmental path cleared for great
nicobar Mega project this is this news
article is from the 10th of October
which is about a month or so ago so it's
a major infrastructure and tourism
project uh which has received the green
signal from the union environment
Ministries committee or whatever yeah uh
there's gonna be Eco tourism there's
going to be tourism Coastal tourism
green and recreational defense ICT
airport all those things
so this shows you where it's going to be
right this is the uh there are a couple
of national parks there all named after
Foreigners for some reason
and
no I would not like to subscribe okay
here it is
so the the red region or the orange
region over here on the map is where the
project is going to be uh that's the
project area
so we're gonna have uh
a port obviously
there's gonna be an airport which will
have a dual it's going to be a dual use
airport which is going to have a
military use and civilian use as well
there are many airports in India which
are dual use airports many of them for
instance I believe uh the airport there
is an airport in Assam the silchar
airport which is a military airport and
it's also used for civilian civilian
aircraft civilian flights then the lay
airport in ladakh if you land there you
will see military planes all over the
place so there are many dual use
airports in India so this airport is
also going to be a dual use airport
there's gonna be a a major port that
will be built over here Container
Terminal and various other things so why
is is this significant
so uh like I have said in this
live stream itself and I've said many
times before the Andaman and nicobar
islands and the lectures of islands also
need to be developed these are
Unsinkable aircraft carriers we need to
develop infrastructure there we need to
develop military infrastructure there
willing to develop Air Force and Naval
infrastructure there we can use them for
as major trans shipment ports uh which
could kind of bypass the Colombo Port
which is the only major transmission
shipment port in the in the uh Indian
subcontinent and all that so it's great
for the Indian economy it's great for
Indian security it it will ensure that
India has a major security military
presence in this region we will be able
to uh we could potentially uh have a
bunch of Sukhoi or other aircraft over
there maybe even strategic bombers you
could have um Indian Navy destroyers and
submarines based over their potentially
possibly I am speculating I don't have
any information I'm just telling you yep
ideally we want to do that we want to
have PODS of of
area denial
missiles you know a280 bubbles around
this region so that if the Chinese try
to uh enter the region with with
malified intentions we could deal with
them appropriately so all this needs to
happen so clearly this is a step in that
direction it's a very welcome step it's
a very good step I I commend the
government of India for taking the step
there will be all kinds of a position so
let me let's take a look I showed you
this article let me show you a whole
different article so this article was
from a publication called what is called
Monga Bay whatever let me show you
a different article about the same uh
same
project here's what there's a different
perspective then this is from the Hindu
Front Line the hindu.com massive
infrastructure project threatens the
great nicobar Island so in their opinion
this is a great threat to the nicobar
islands biodiversity it's stripping the
protected status of of some parts of the
island and uh yeah there are these
monkeys macaques and various other
animals over there the the tree shru
which could be threatened Turtles Olive
Ridley
Turtle hatchling and all that
anthropogenic threats threats to the to
the local people and so on
so that's what this this article is
trying to tell us it's an alarmist
article it's telling us this is a
terrible project so what's the truth
any development project will have a
certain environmental impact yes
that is true but it is necessary for
India's national security
and the government I believe is
committed to to
reforest another part of the island or
any other or some other place in to make
up for the for the lost forest cover
so it is unfortunate but it has to
happen yes it will it will impact some
of the local uh tribes people who have
been living for a very long time on the
island but it is necessary it is
necessary for the long-term National
Security and for the for the continued
survival essentially of India and for
India's
long-term Ambitions yeah to become a
major world power once again it has to
happen
so it's going to be great for for the
National Security of India from the Air
Force perspective from the Navy
perspective from the area denial and in
missile launching perspective you know
it gives you if you have a bunch of
missiles there
we have a whole lot of missiles we have
a whole bouquet of missiles of various
characteristics we have the supersonic
brahmos missile which will come in an
extended range as well we have cruise
missiles like the nearby which is under
development we have various ballistic
missiles you launch things from there
they're gonna have a whole different
range
and so it's great for the security of
the nation it's going to be great for
the economy because it's going to be a
transshipment hub so that will bring in
lots of revenue for India there will be
an environmental impact which is
which is inevitable it will
Force some of the local indigenous
tribes people to have to move to a
different region I'm sure the government
will do the right thing for them
and and and and give them a different
place to live in on the same Island the
island is quite large so I am sure all
of this will be taken care of by the
government but overall from the from the
perspective of the Indian national
interest it's a very good development
and I'm really happy to see this so
that's what I have to say about this
foreign
this is from Twitter so uh I had said on
Twitter in response to somebody else's
tweet that Australia is not a US Ally
Australia is U.S property
so in response to my tweet this uh
gentleman called shardul Sharma says
that Australia is also one of the
richest places on Earth and the
Australians don't have any issues being
U.S properties so chill chill bro chill
chill
so this shardul Sharma Sharma sounds
like an Indian person maybe he is an
Australian citizen I'm not sure but he
has decided to speak on behalf of the
Australian people and he's saying that
it's okay to be U.S property as long as
you're rich so chill
now here's a different comment from an
actual Australian person he says that
it's from Paul Rankin he says that
Australia has a permanent rotation of
about 15
000 U.S troops in case we Australians
decide we don't like their corporations
what is this Australian gentleman saying
he is saying that Australia is under
permanent U.S military occupation
uh and if you look at it deeper
Australia is essentially U.S property so
let's take a look at some of the see
some evidence of that yeah
um
so this is an article
from an Australian news site yes
it says that it says U.S military bases
in Australia protecting us or putting us
at risk the U.S has a network of
secretive military bases across
Australia and something it could plunge
Australia into a war the U.S is
strengthening a network of secretive
military bases across Australia and so
on and so forth yeah and it's got some
some images of that let's take a look at
a different article
foreign
the Asia Pacific journal the U.S
military presence in Australia is
asymmetric Alliance Corp cooperation and
its Alternatives it says that as in
Japan and Korea
this involves Australia governments
identifying Australian national
interests with those of the US the
integration of the Australian military
military forces organizationally and
technologically with U.S forces and
rapid and extensive expansion of an
American Military presence in Australia
itself so once again this is alluding to
U.S military occupation of Australia
let's take a look at how many military
bases the U.S has in Australia
what is it true so this is a Wikipedia
article a standard disclaimer Village
Wikipedia is not always reliable we have
to be use it very carefully if we do use
it so
Australia pine Gap Naval Communication
System Harold e Holt robots and barracks
and so on and so forth there's a whole
bunch of
bases that are listed over here but
there are many more bases that are not
listed as is evident from the other
articles that we just saw uh let's take
a look at one more article to drive home
the point that we are trying to make
this is this article over here
it's uh once again from an Australian
news site U.S military plans for greater
presence in Australia as it confronts
Chinese China's power and so so plans
for U.S military upgrades of Australian
defense sites have been highlighted in a
long-awaited pentagon study
and so on new rotational fighter and
bomber aircraft deployments and so on so
I think you get the point that I am
trying to make that Australia is under
permanent U.S military occupation
Australia does not have an independent
foreign policy in Australia's economic
and military policy is integrated with
that of the U.S in its foreign policy is
also integrated with that of the U.S
which means that Australia is an
extension of the US and if you look
deeper into it Australia is essentially
owned by the US even though technically
it's owned by the British crown which
means it is a property of King Charles
the third or whatever the he whatever
number he is King Charles II
but de facto if you look at it from the
realistic perspective Australia is owned
by the U.S so now uh this fine gentleman
my friend shardo over here says that
it's okay if it's own if it's U.S
property it's the one of the richest
places on Earth so chill so what this
gentleman is saying is that it's okay to
be owned by somebody else as long as you
are prosperous you're rich then you have
a good life
so look at it like this it's entirely
possible for your country to be occupied
by a foreign nation and yet for the
people of your country to have
Prosperity look at Japan Japan has been
under permanent hardcore U.S occupation
since 1945. it doesn't have an
independent policy
its economic policy is dictated by the
U.S its internal policy also to a large
extent is dictated by the U.S to a large
extent
and yet Japan is the world's most
technologically advanced Nation its
people are very prosperous compared to
Nations like India very rich very high
GDP per capita they have complete
Financial Freedom they can choose to go
and move anywhere in the world if they
want so individually each individual in
Japan is free
each Japanese citizen is free and rich
and prosperous and yet the nation is
enslaved by a foreign power it is
perfectly possible for of for a an
enslaved Nation to have free people
so is that the right thing is that good
as long as I am free as long as I am
rich and as long as I can do what I want
I am perfectly fine with my nation being
enslaved by another this is called slave
mindedness this is the slave mentality
that people talk about so this is what
we are witnessing here it's unfortunate
that so many Indians suffer from this
slave mentality
so unfortunate and that's why I keep
saying please raise your standards we
need higher standards in India so that's
what I have to say about this yep
okay saurabh says how did the britishers
mold the varunajate system into the
caste system we know that caste comes
from the root word Casta which is the
Portuguese word what's the difference
between Casta and the Verna jati system
and Rahul says
Rahul says Oh What A you are
speaking Abhijit if the cast system was
invented by the British then why do The
Nepalese follow the system even though
they were never colonized by the British
and one of the reasons for the creation
of Sikhism is the caste issues in
Hinduism check your fast facts first of
which is you're talking
this is a problem I I face almost every
day
and no matter how many facts I put forth
people are unwilling to to see
Sikhism was not created in a response to
us it's some imagined caste system in
Hinduism see
sticky
was a response to foreign imperialism
and foreign occupation of India by the
Turks
that's
that was the purpose of the of the of
the creation of sikhi or what we call
Sikhism it has nothing to do with
so-called caste system The Nepalese
don't follow a caste system they follow
the word system now let me once again
put some facts in case some of you may
understand it I I know that most of my
audience is really intelligent which is
why they've watched the Afghan show but
uh in case there are some newcomers or
some
as well let me
put some facts
let's let's take a look at this so if I
show you an article or a book written by
an Indian you will not believe it this
is part of the mental colonization if I
show you something an article or a book
written by an Indian you will not
believe it so I have to show you
articles and books written by foreigners
that's the unfortunate
mental colonization that we see in India
so here's one the Western foundations of
the caste system
it's by Martin farick Duncan jalke and
and two Indians right
so this is a book I would recommend that
you read because it talks about the
Western foundation of the caste system
let me show you a review of this book
right that's a book summary as well I'll
put it on the screen so that you can
study it yourself I would request you to
do some reading of your own yes this is
a book summary
you can look it up online you know what
the title is Western foundations of the
cast system and it's a four part review
this is the first part of the of the
review this is one article please study
this you need to do some reading of your
own to understand things you cannot
simply blindly believe what you have
been taught which you have not really
studied on your own so this is something
I would recommend that you read now let
me give you some more references there
is another book once again I'm giving
you a foreign offer because you will not
trust Indian authors because you have
this inferiority complex some of you
this book is called casts of Mind
colonialism and the making of Modern
India it's by Nicholas B Ducks who is a
very prominent and and very well
respected American academic yes it's
called castes of mine colonialism and
the making of Modern India
let me show you some more I I would like
you to read this
read all of this that I'm telling you
don't trust me don't Don't fact check
what I am telling you and how will you
fact check by looking at by reading all
this by studying all this here's a
different article it's uh it's by a
person called Akbar dosanj cast as a
colonial creation the discussion around
UK legislation on caste discrimination
is too quick to forget how much it was
bitten which invented the system in the
first place the so-called caste system
the words of the British superintendent
of the 1921 census are still poignant
poignant today we pigeon hold everybody
by caste and if we could not find a true
cast for them we labeled them with the
name of the hereditary occupation we
deplore the caste system and its effect
on social and economic problems but we
the British are largely responsible for
the system we deplore
do you not do you see this
let me show you some more
it's so sad that I have to keep on doing
this every single time and people just
don't understand
this is an article
called the Indian caste system in the
British
I would like you to read this article
please
it says I'm just showing you a small
except moreover as will be seen later in
this paper it appears that the caste
system extent in the late 19th and early
20th century has been altered as a
result of British accent actions so that
it increasingly took on the
characteristics that were ascribed to it
by the British
do you see that
please study this article in its
entirety you want to understand things
you have to do some research some work
of your own here's one more
I'm gonna I'm gonna throw a whole bunch
of data at you today because I'm tired
of this nonsense
do you trust the BBC
yes you trust the BBC I'm sure it's not
Indian right so you it's from from the
UK so you have to trust it Viewpoint how
the British reshaped India's caste
system yeah and he has an accept
uh in a new book The Truth About Us
whatever I show how the social
categories of religion and caste as they
are perceived in modern day India were
developed during the British colonial
rule at a time when information was cars
and the colonizers power over
information was absolute so once again
it tells you that the British created
this so-called caste system right
okay let me show you some more yeah
let's let's see let's see the Greek
perspective because the the British
perspective is not enough I'm sure for
you all
so this is uh the 300 BC book Indica by
meghastanis dispels caste theories of
India so what does it tell us right uh
what's Point number five the Indians
this is what megastines the the Greek
ambassador to India during the mauryan
times this is what he said
this is what he wrote the Indians
generally were divided into seven
categories the wise men which is
interpreted as brahmins then the farmers
the herdsmen The Artisans the soldiers
the old Lookers and the government
officials including Army and Navy
officers there were seven categories not
castes two and a half thousand years ago
there was no caste system right there
were seven classes not four not four
seven classes that's what the Greeks
found in India let me show you more let
me show you more come on let's do this
let's do it properly today
this is an inscription from birchability
Agra sikri about a thousand years ago
okay there was no cast there was only
gotra one thousand years ago
let's see what this inscription says
there is an image of the inscription and
there are translations into Hindi and
English om siddam the shresthis of
installed the image of Shri Shruti Devi
Saraswati in the habitat of the muni so
and so forth and so on so forth it does
not mention any caste any so-called cast
in it only mentions gotra which means
the lineage the lineage the family line
let's see some more this is an article
by Dr David froley he's an American he's
a Hindu so you may not trust him perhaps
right you need somebody who's not a
Hindu
but let me show it to you anyway why
Varna is not cast this is by Dr David
Frawley it's from about six years ago
please read the article I'm not going to
read it out over here so this is another
reference that I'm offering you let's
see some more let us see some more do
you know that there were four
divisions of society in China
what does it remind you of four
occupations
four categories of the people
was an occupation classification used in
ancient China by confusion and legalist
Scholars yes and you find that later in
it's outside China in Japan which the
so-called Japanese castes these were not
castes but in English they call
everything a caste
this is the myopic world view of the
West they are saying that the Japanese
also had cast these were not castes but
they are calling the you know the
nomenclature they are using is caste
now people so that cast is bad because
it's all about hereditary occupations
right yeah
so what about the the English
occupations England surnames they
derived from occupations hereditary
occupations
most of them originated in medieval
towns and villages in England like
Carter like Hayward like Thatcher Smith
Taylor yeah boat ride Cartwright
shipwright Wainwright Turner Goddard
Cowherd Webb Webster Weaver
Dempster Franklin Knight Marshall page
squire
Chamberlain Duke Earl Pope priest Etc
these are all hereditary occupations
that have been passed on from generation
to generation just like in India in
England but in India it's bad in England
it's fine right because hereditary
passing on off anything is bad because
that is the caste system apparently
uh I I hope I have
I have given enough information for all
of you to use your own intelligence to
understand what the truth is about
please do some reading of your own
please do some deep study of your own
don't fall prey to dogmatic thinking
which is accepting the results and in
the products of other people's thinking
please think on your own please study
things yourselves otherwise don't come
and say such things oh what
what you are speaking about I
mean come on come on so yeah that's what
I have to say about caste
and about Nepal Nepal follows the jati
Verna system jati means whatever lineage
you have essentially gotra there are
various jatis there are there's a whole
bunch of jati's hundreds maybe thousands
of jatis in in the Indian subcontinent
yeah
means whatever occupation you have so
various jatis would have different
vernas within them it's a very complex
system the British who don't understand
it that's why they oversimplify it into
forecasts
that's what they did I think I have
demonstrated I have given you enough
references please study them spend a few
weeks reading all this only then will
you understand the truth it is very easy
to listen to misinform people by
oversimplifying things and then to
counter the misinformation you have to
study you need to spend lots of time
studying so in case you respect
yourselves and would like to actually
learn something the truth then please
study this that's what I would recommend
and request you to do
foreign
the question but asking a different
question someone says China will be
sending monkeys into space to see the
outcomes of reproduction up there what
are your thoughts on this and should
India and the rest of the world do it
without thinking about ethical issues we
need to explore space mining as well
Aerospace medicine will get a boom in
the future so yeah to answer this
question China is sending monkeys is
planning to send monkeys into space to
see
the effects or see how the environment
of of zero gravity or microgravity
affects reproduction
so they intend those monkeys to
reproduce in space see right now we are
an Earthbound species we make very brief
forays into Earth orbit only if only a
handful of people have been into Earth
orbit and only a handful of people have
broken free of
of
have broken free for that orbit and go
into moon orbit or on the surface of the
Moon so
um
but eventually we would like to become a
space-faring species
for that we would have to spend extended
amount of amounts of time in space and
in the future maybe we would need to
reproduce in space as well because
reproduction reproduction is is
essential to human to the Survivor of
the human species and monkeys are the
are our closest relatives I mean the
apes are even closer but various monkeys
also can serve the purpose their biology
is very similar to that of that of
humans so the Chinese want to want to
see so it means the Chinese are
ambitious they would like to see how it
goes what is the effect of microgravity
or zero gravity on the reproductive
process of very closely uh very close
species that are very close to us yeah
so it's all about the long term future
it's all about planning for the future
in the future we would we would perhaps
want to send human beings on Long
voyages across space Maybe in the future
to a different star system as well
perhaps definitely to Mars Mars the
gravity on Mars is much lower than that
on Earth yes and so one way of seeing of
seeing how it goes is to have monkeys
reproducing space and see what is the
outcome
what does it have any uh does it have
any deleterious effects on the viability
of the fetus is the is the fetus is the
child born
normal or are there any defects what is
the effect of so of cosmic rays and the
solar radiation of the radiation on on
the mother on on the monkeys on the
child all these things need to be looked
at yeah ethical issues when China
doesn't really care about ethical issues
um the Americans also don't care about
ethical issues they have sent monkeys
into space they have various animals
must have died in Space the Russians
sent the first dog Leica into space
where she died
um and so on yeah so you know
and all all kinds of Nations continue to
conduct animal experiments animal
experimentation which can be extremely
cool yeah so unfortunately we are the
dominant species on the planet and we
humans
we would I mean if you if you look at it
culturally from the Indian cultural
perspective we would never want to do
this but other nations don't have any
such qualms and that's how it goes
so yes uh
the Chinese will find out what happens
and hopefully we will learn something
from that I mean I'm sure they'll make
the results public if not we'll see
so yeah these are this is something that
is the future
and uh so yeah so we do need to explore
space mining which is going to happen
perhaps in the next 100 200 years it's
still in the far future but India needs
to establish a presence in Earth orbit a
space station first of all we need to
start our human space flight program we
need to create our own space station we
need to as soon as possible establish a
presence on the moon as well step by
step step by step yeah
so yes India needs to catch up India has
the ability the capability to do that
but yeah we are kind of slightly behind
right now but I'm sure we can catch up
rapidly ISRO is a very capable
organization as we know very well
okay we are almost at the two hour mark
I had a whole lot of other questions
that I wanted to answer unfortunately
I'm not able to answer them today
because we have reached almost the end
of today's uh live stream so I apologize
to those people whose questions I had
selected they will not know it but yeah
sorry let me take some live chat
questions as is our convention right so
if you have any questions
that we would like to ask me which are
which uh you have not asked then you
could ask me right now in the live chat
and I will take a look I will answer
maybe two or three questions
uh yes yes ISRO is great I agree ISRO is
wonderful and we are very proud of
Israel
um
give me five minutes then we'll do bye
I'll take a few questions uh
okay Prasad is asking about the Iran
Hypersonic missile so the Iranians have
uh
declared that they have tested
successfully a Hypersonic cruise missile
ballistic missile I'm not sure it's it's
obviously a cruise missile ballistic
missiles are Ultra Hypersonic yeah but
the re-entry velocity is about marked
23 or so which is incredibly uh High
Velocity so I'm sure they're talking
about a cruise missile of some kind
which is a Hypersonic missile good good
for them
did they get help from from somewhere
we don't know uh
two places from which they could have
possibly got help one is China possibly
and one could possibly be Russia I'm not
sure the Russians would want to share
such advanced technology with the policy
over Parsi friends but maybe it's
Chinese who did that because the Chinese
are investing big time in in Iran
a 40 billion plus dollar
uh deal they signed recently and so like
the past two three years or so maybe
2018 2019 thereabouts so uh or maybe
they did it on their own in which case
kudos to them so Iran is a very
ambitious Nation uh the the
Iranian government I'm sure would like
to in the long run re-establish some
form of the of the Persian Empire so
yeah they are a very ambitious nation
and they
um they they have good technology they
have been developing these drones which
are very effective they've sold those
drones to the Shahid whatever number it
is drones they sold a bunch of them to
Russia and the Russians are using them
in the conflict in Ukraine because they
don't want to use the Air Force and so
on so Iran is doing well they are
developing drones and they seem to have
developed a Hypersonic cruise missile
good for them good for them
all right
um
what else do we have uh
chiranjeev says let's try it started
movement of burning two books my
experiments but with Truth by Mr Gandhi
and Bharat a code by Mr nehru you know
what um
um even bad things need to be preserved
is an example of of what bad is
um
so yeah I mean
burning which see if you burn books and
if you ban books you kind of forget your
past your past may have been good it may
have been bad especially if it's bad if
you have to ensure you never forget it
so I would say it would be kind of I
would I would venture to say that it
would be kind of counterproductive to
burn books of banned books keep them
preserve them as an example of the bad
times that India went through we had
people like Mr Gandhi we had people like
Mr nehru who were not the most ideal
greatest of course
you know how it is you know not the best
examples of leadership and these books
uh give us insights into their mindset
so it's something we should actually
Preserve
and study
because it gives you an insight into
what went wrong with India
in the past
um
that's a beautiful Rhino uh this one
here yes it's a great right now I got it
from Assam I had gone to silchar to nit
silchar where the wonderful people there
presented me with this rhino and I
thought I'd put it over here because
it's a great it's a great Rhino it's an
awesomest Rhino anybody from Assam great
all right let's take maybe one more
question
says who is better for India Imran Khan
or Shabbat Sharif
um see the Pakistan prime minister
doesn't it doesn't matter who he or she
is they are more or less powerless
and it's always the Army and the isi
that essentially calls the shots so it
doesn't matter see Mr Modi did not ever
bother to even have a phone conversation
with Mr Imran Khan not even once it's if
I'm not mistaken because it doesn't
matter who's in power it doesn't matter
who is the prime minister because the
person is powerless that person is
nothing more than a puppet so whether
it's Imran Khan or Nawaz Sharif or
Shabad Sharif or whoever else it may be
it doesn't matter they are all the same
for India
yeah
so that would be my answer
what would I say about China's recent
Aid to Pakistan I have been saying that
Pakistan is now a U.S visa state so why
is that why are the Chinese giving Aid
to Pakistan well they will try to fight
the development and they will try to
throw more carrots at the pakistanis
they will not give up without a fight
and the pakistanis the kind of nation
they are they are always happy to get
money from whichever place it comes but
it at the end of the day it all depends
on who has the bigger stick and who has
a deeper Pockets do the Chinese have
deeper Pockets than the Americans than
Uncle Sam not at all
do the Chinese have a bigger stick than
Uncle Sam once again no the Americans
have the deeper pockets and the
Americans have the bigger stick so let
the Chinese throw some money a few
billion dollars once again in Pakistan
which is not a donation which this this
Aid the so-called Aid is actually alone
it is
additional debt that Pakistan is taking
it will have to repay that money it's
not Aid
rights of the pakistanis are deeping a
digger or or digging a deeper hole for
themselves in form of more Chinese loans
and
that's just how it is but at the end of
the day they're going to remain U.S for
sales because now they are useful to the
Americans ones again and that's where we
are
all right my dear friends thank you for
all the questions thank you for being on
the live stream thank you very much and
uh this is the end of today's live
stream I will see you very soon next
week
Saturday Sunday until then take care
and see you later bye